Frau Holle (1857)

A widow had two daughters, the one was beautifulpositive, female and industriouspositive, female, the other uglynegative, female and lazynegative, female. She greatly favoredpassive, female, neutral the uglynegative, female, lazynegative, female girl, because she was her own daughter. And the other one had to do all the work, and be the Cinderellanegative, female of the house.

Every day the poornegative, female girl had to sitpassive, female, neutral by a well, next to the highway, and spin so muchactive, female, hesitant that her fingers bled. Now it happened that one day the reel was completely bloody, so she dippedactive, female, neutral it in the well, to wash it off, but it droppedpassive, female, neutral out of her hand and fell in. She criedpassive, female, neutral, ran to her stepmotheractive, female, neutral, and told her of the mishap. She scolded heractive, female, neutral so sharply, and was so mercilessnegative, female that she said, "Since you have let the reel fall in, you must fetch it out again."

Then the girl went back to the well, and did not know what to do. Terrifiednegative, female, she jumped into the wellactive, female, hesitant to get the reel. She lost her senses. And when she awokepassive, female, neutral and came to herself again, she was in a beautiful meadow where the sun was shining, and there were many thousands of flowers. She walked across this meadow and came to an oven full of bread. The bread called out, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time." So she stepped up to it, and with a baker's peel took everything outactive, female, neutral, one loaf after the other.

After that she walked further and came to a tree laden with apples. "Shake me. Shake me. We apples are all ripe." cried the tree. So she shook the treeactive, female, neutral until the apples fell as though it were raining apples. When none were left in the tree, she gathered themactive, female, neutral into a pile, and then continued on her way.

Finally she came to a small house. An old woman was peering out from inside. She had very large teethnegative, female, which frightenednegative, female the girl, and she wanted to run away. But the old woman called out to her, "Don't be afraid, dear child. Stay here with me, and if you do my housework in an orderly fashion, it will go well with you. Only you must take care to make my bed well and shake it diligently until the feathers fly, then it will snow in the world. I am Frau Holle."

Because the old woman spoke so kindlynegative, female to her, the girl took heart, agreed, and started in her service. The girl took care of everything to Frau Holle's satisfaction and always shook her featherbed vigorouslyactive, female, neutral until the feathers flew about like snowflakes. Therefore she had a good life with her: no angry words, and boiled or roast meat every day.

Now after she had been with Frau Holle for a time, she became sadnegative, female. At first she did not know what was the matter with her, but at last she determined that it was homesicknessnegative, female. Even though she was many thousands of times better off here than at home, still she had a yearning to return. Finally she said to the old woman, "I have such a longing for home, and even though I am very well off here, I cannot stay longer. I must go up again to my own people."

Frau Holle said, "I am pleased that you long for your home again, and because you have served me so faithfullypositive, female, I will take you back myself." With that she took her by the hand and led heractive, female, neutral to a large gate.

The gate was opened, and while the girl was standing under it, an immense rain of gold fell, and all the gold stuck to her, so that she was completely covered with it. "This is yours because you have been so industriouspositive, female," said Frau Holle, and at the same time she gave her back the reel which had fallen into the well.

With that the gate was closed and the girl found herself above on earth, not far from her mother's house. And as she entered the yard the rooster, sitting on the well, cried:

Cock-a-doodle-doo, Our golden girl is here anew.

Then she went inside to her mother, and as she arrived all covered with gold, she was well received, both by her mother and her sister. The girl told all that had happened to her, and when the mother heard how she had come to the great wealth, she wanted to achieveactive, female, neutral the same fortune for the other, the uglynegative, female and lazynegative, female daughter. She made her go and sitpassive, female, neutral by the well and spin. And to make her reel bloody, the lazy girl pricked her fingers and shoved her hand into a thorn bush. Then she threw the reel into the well, and jumped in herselfactive, female, eager.

Like the other girl, she too came to the beautiful meadow and walked along the same path. When she came to the oven, the bread cried again, "Oh, take me out. Take me out, or else I'll burn. I've been thoroughly baked for a long time."

But the lazy girl answered, "As if I would want to get all dirty," and walked awaypassive, female, neutral.

Soon she came to the apple tree. It cried out, "Oh, shake me. Shake me. We apples are all ripe."

But she answered, "Oh yes, one could fall on my head," and with that she walked onpassive, female, eager.

When she came to Frau Holle's house, she was not afraid, because she had already heard about her large teethnegative, female, and she immediately began to work for her. On the first day she forced herself, was industriouspositive, female, and obeyed Frau Holle, when she said something to her, because she was thinking about all the gold that she would give her. But on the second day she already began to be lazynegative, female, on the third day even more so, and then she didn't even want to get up in the morning. She did not make the bed for Frau Holle, the way she was supposed to, and she did not shake it until the feathers flew. Frau Holle soon became tired of this and dismissed her of her duties. This was just what the lazy girl wanted, for she thought that she would now get the rain of gold.

Frau Holle led heractive, female, neutral too to the gate. She stood beneath it, but instead of gold, a large kettle full of pitch spilled over her. "That is the reward for your services," said Frau Holle, and closed the gate.

Then the lazy girl went home, entirely covered with pitch. As soon as the rooster on the well saw her, he cried out:

Cock-a-doodle-doo, Our dirty girl is here anew.

And the pitch stuck fast to her, and did not come off as long as she lived.

Girl without Hands

A miller, who was so poor that he had nothing more than his mill and a large apple tree which stood behind it,negative, male went into the forest to gather woodactive, male, neutral. There he was approached by an old manneutral, male, who said, "Why do you torment yourself so? I will make you rich if you will sign over to me that which is standing behind your mill. I will come and claim it in three years." The miller thought, "That is my apple tree," agreed, and signed it over to the man.active, male, eager

When he came home, his wifeneutral, female said to him, "Miller, where did all the wealth come from that suddenly has filled every chest and cupboard in our house?"

"I received it from an old man in the forest by signing over to him that which is standing behind the mill."

"Husband!" said the woman, terrifiednegative, female. "This is going to be very bad. The old man was the devil, and he had our daughter in mind, who was just then standing behind the mill sweeping the yard."

Now the miller's daughter was very beautiful and pious.positive, female Three years later when the devil came, early in the morning, and wanted to take her, she had drawn a circle around herself with chalk and had washed herself clean.active, female, eager

Therefore the devil could not approach her, and angrilynegative, male he said to the miller, "Keep wash water away from her, so she cannot wash herself any more, and I can have power over her."

The miller was frightenednegative, male and did what he was toldactive, male, neutral. The next day the devil returned, but she had weptpassive, female, neutral into her hands and washedpassive, female, neutral herself with her tears, and was entirely clean.

Because the devil still could not approach her, he was very angrynegative, male, and orderedactive, male, neutral the miller, "Chop off her hands, so I can get to her."

The miller was horrifiednegative, male and answered, "How could I chop off my dear child's hands? No, I will not do it."

"Then do you know what? I will take you, if you don't do it!"

That frightenednegative, male the miller terribly, and driven by fear he promisedactive, male, neutral to do what the devil had ordered. He went to his daughter and said, "My child, the devil will take me if I don't chop off both your hands, and I have promised him that I will do it. I beg for your forgiveness."

"Father," she said, "do with me what you will," stretched forth her hands, and let him chop them offpassive, female, neutral.

The devil came a third time, but she had weptpassive, female, neutral so long onto her stumps, that she was still entirely clean, and the devil had lost all power over her.

The miller, because he had become so wealthy through her, promised to take the best care of her for the rest of her life, but she did not want to remain there.

"I must leave here," she said. "Compassionate people will give me enough to keep me alive."

She had the chopped-off hands tied to her back, and she set forthactive, female, eager with the rising sun, walking the entire day until evening, when she came to the king's garden. There was a gap in the garden hedge. She went inside, found a fruit tree, shook it with her body until the apples fell to the ground, bent over and picked them up with her teeth, and ate them.active, female, neutral Thus she lived for two days, but on the third day the garden watchmen saw her, captured her, and threw her into prison.

The next morning she was brought before the king and sentenced to be banished from the land, but the prince said, "Wait, wouldn't it be better to let her tend the chickens in the courtyard?" So she stayed there for a time and tended the chickens. The prince saw her often and grew very fond of her.

Meanwhile the time came when he was to get married. Messengers were sent everywhere in the world to find him a beautiful bride. "You needn't look so far and wide," he said. "I know where one is very nearby."

The oldneutral, male king ponderedpassive, male, neutral this back and forth, but he could not think of a single maiden in his kingdom who was both beautiful and rich, "You surely don't want to marry the one who tends the chickens in the courtyard?" But his son declaredactive, male, eager that he would marry no one else, so finally the king had to agree. Soon afterward he diedpassive, male, neutral, and the prince succeeded him as king and lived happily for a time with his wife.

Once the king had to go away to war, and during his absence his wife gave birthactive, female, neutral to a beautifulpositive, male child. She sent a messenger with a letter telling her husband the joyful news. On the way the messenger stopped to rest by a brook and fell asleep. The devil, who was still trying to harm her, came to him and exchanged the letter with one that stated that the queen had given birth to a changelingnegative, male. The king was very saddened to read this, but he wrote that the queen and the child should be well cared for until his return. The messenger started back with this letter. When he stopped to rest at the same spot and fell asleep, the devil again appeared, this time exchangingactive, male, eager the king's letter with one that ordered the queen and the child to be driven from the kingdom. This had to be done, however much the people all weptpassive, mixed, neutral with sorrow.

"I did not come here to become queen," she said. "I have no luck, and I demand none. Just tie my child and my hands onto my back, and I will set forth into the world."

That evening she came to a place in a thick forest where a goodpositive, male old man was sitting by a spring. "Be so kindhearted as to hold my child to my breast until I have nursed him," she said.

The man did that, after which he said to her, "Go to that thick tree over there and wrap your maimed arms around it three times!" And when she had done this, her hands grewpassive, female, neutral back on. Then he showed her a house. "You can live there," he said, "but do not go outside, and do not open the door for anyone unless he asks three times to come in, for God's sake."

Meanwhile the king returned home and discovered how he had been deceived. Accompanied by a single servant he set forthactive, female, eager, and after a long journey he finally happened, one night, into the same forest where the queen was living, but he did not know that she was so close to him. "There is a little light from a house back there," said his servant. "We can rest there."

"No," said the king. "I do not want to rest so long, but rather to continue searching for my wife. I cannot rest until I find her."

But the servant beggedactive, male, eager so much and complainedactive, male, eager so about his weariness that out of compassion, the king gave inpassive, male, hesitant. When they came to the house, the moon was shining, and they saw the queen standing by the window. "That must be our queen; she looks just like her," said the servant, "but I see now that she is not the one, for this one has hands."

The servant asked her for shelter, but she refusedactive, female, neutral, because he had not asked "for God's sake." He was about to go on and seek another place for their night's lodging when the king himself came up and said, "Let me in, for God's sake!"

"I cannot let you in until you have asked me three time, for God's sake," she replied. And after the king had asked two more times, she opened the door. His littleneutral, male son ran to him and led him in to his mother. The king recognized her immediately as his belovedpositive, male wife. The next morning they all journeyed together back to their kingdom, and as soon as they had left the house, it disappeared behind them.

Hans-My-Hedgehog (1815)

Once upon a time there was a peasant who had money and land enough, but as richpositive, male as he was, there was still something missing from his happinessnegatve, male: He had no children with his wife. Often when he went to the city with the other peasants, they would mock him and ask him why he had no children. He finally became angrynegative, male, and when he returned home, he said, "I will have a child, even if it is a hedgehog."

Then his wife had a baby, and the top half was a hedgehog and the bottom half a boy. When she saw the baby, she was horrifiednegative, female and said, "Now see what you have wished upon us!"

The man said, "It cannot be helped. The boy must be baptized, but we cannot ask anyone to be his godfather."

The woman said, "And the only name that we can give him is Hans-My-Hedgehogactive, female, hesitant."

When he was baptized, the pastor said, "Because of his quills he cannot be given an ordinary bed." So they put a little straw behind the stove and laid him in it. And he could not drink from his mother, for he would have stuck her with his quills. He lay there behind the stove for eight yearspassive, male, neutral, and his father grew tired of himpassive, male, neutral, and thought, "if only he would die." But he did not die, but just lay there.

Now it happened that there was a fair in the city, and the peasant wanted to go. He askedactive, male, neutral his wife what he should bring her.

"A little meat, some bread rolls, and things for the household," she said. Then he askedactive, male, neutral the servant girl, and she wanted a pair of slippers and some fancy stockings.

Finally, he also saidactive, male, neutral, "Hans-My-Hedgehog, what would you like?"

"Father," he said, "bring me some bagpipes."

When the peasant returned homepassive, male, neutral he gave his wife what he had brought for her, meat and bread rolls. Then he gave the servant girl the slippers and fancy stockings. And finally he went behind the stove and gave Hans-My-Hedgehog the bagpipes.

When Hans-My-Hedgehog had them, he said, "Father, go to the blacksmith's and have my cock-rooster shod, then I will ride away and never again come back." The father was happy to get rid of him, so he had his rooster shodactive, male, eager, and when it was done, Hans-My-Hedgehog climbedactive, male, eager on it and rode away. He tookactive, male, neutral pigs and donkeys with him, to tend in the forest.

In the forest the rooster flew into a tall tree with him. There he satpassive, male, neutral and watchedpassive, male, neutral over the donkeys and the pigs. He sat there for yearspassive, male, neutral, until finally the herd had grown large. His father knew nothing about him. While sittingpassive, male, neutral in the tree, he played his bagpipesactive, male, neutral and made beautiful music.

One day a king came by. He was lost and heard the music. He was amazed to hear it, and sent a servantpassive, male, eager to look around and see where it was coming from. He looked hereactive, male, neutral and there but only saw a little animal sitting high in a tree. It looked like a rooster up there with a hedgehog sitting on it making the music.

The king said to the servantpassive, male, neutral that he should ask him why he was sitting there, and if he knew the way back to his kingdom. Then Hans-My-Hedgehog climbedactive, male, neutral down from the tree and told him that he would show him the way if the king would promisepassive, male, neutral in writing to give him the first thing that greeted him at the royal court upon his arrival home.

The king thought, "I can do that easily enough. Hans-My-Hedgehog cannot understand writing, and I can put down what I want to."

Then the king took pen and ink and wrote somethingactive, male, eager, and after he had done so, Hans-My-Hedgehog showed him the wayactive, male, neutral, and he arrived safely at home. His daughter saw him coming from afar, and was so overjoyed that she ranactive, female, eager to meet him and kissedactive, female, eager him. He thought about Hans-My-Hedgehog and told her what had happened, that he was supposed to have promised the first thing that greeted him to a strange animal that rode a rooster and made beautiful music. But instead he had written that this would not happen, for Hans-My-Hedgehog could not read. The princess was happypositive, female about this, and said that it was a good thing, for she would not have gone with him in any event.

Hans-My-Hedgehog tended the donkeys and pigs, was of good cheerpositive, male, and sat in the tree blowing on his bagpipespassive, male, neutral.

Now it happened that another king came this way with his servants and messengers. He too got lostpassive, male, neutral and did not know the way back home because the forest was so large. He too heard the beautiful music from afar, and asked one of his messengerspassive, male, eager to go and see what it was and where it was coming from. The messenger ranactive, male, neutral to the tree where he saw Hans-My-Hedgehog astride the cock-rooster. The messenger asked him what he was doing up there.

"I am tendingpassive, male, neutral my donkeys and pigs. What is it that you want?" replied Hans-My-Hedgehog.

The messenger said that they were lost and could not find their way back to their kingdom, and asked him if he could not show them the way.

Then Hans-My-Hedgehog climbedactive, male, neutral down from the tree with his rooster and told the old king that he would show him the way if he would give him the thing that he first met at home before the royal castle.

The king said yes and signed a promiseactive, male, hesitant to Hans-My-Hedgehog.

When that was done, Hans-My-Hedgehog rode ahead on his rooster showing them the wayactive, male, neutral, and the king safely reached his kingdom. When the king arrived at his court there was great joy. Now he had an only daughter who was very beautifulpositive, fenale. She ran out to himactive, female, eager, threw her arms around his neckactive, female, eager and kissedactive, female, eager him, and was ever so happypositive, female that her old father had returned.

She askedactive, female, eager him where he had been during his long absence, and he told heractive, male, neutral how he had lost his way and almost not made it home again, but that as he was making his way through a great forest he had come upon a half hedgehog, half human astride a rooster sitting in a tall tree and making beautiful music who had shown him the way, but whom he had promised whatever first met him at the royal court, and it was she herself, and he was terribly sorrynegative, male.

But she promisedactive, female, hesitant that she would go with him when he came, for the lovepassive, female, eager of her old father.

Hans-My-Hedgehog tended his pigspassive, male, neutral, and the pigs had more pigs, until there were so many that the whole forest was full. Then Hans-My-Hedgehog let his father know that they should empty out all the stalls in the village, because he was comingactive, male, neutral with such a large herd of pigs that everyone who wanted to would be able to take part in the slaughter.

It saddened the father to hear this, for he thought that Hans-My-Hedgehog had long since died. But Hans-My-Hedgehog mounted his cock-roosteractive, male, neutral, drove the pigsactive, male, neutral ahead of himself into the village, and had them butcheredpassive, male, neutral. What a slaughter! What a commotion! They could hear the noise two hours away!

Afterward Hans-My-Hedgehog said, "Father, have my cock-rooster shodpassive, male, neutral a second time at the blacksmith's. Then I will ride awayactive, male, neutral and not come back again as long as I live." So the father had the cock-rooster shodactive, male, neutral, and was happy that Hans-My-Hedgehog was not coming back.

Hans-My-Hedgehog rodeactive, male, neutral into the first kingdom. The king had orderedpassive, male, neutral that if anyone should approach who was carrying bagpipes and riding on a rooster, that he should be shot at, struck down, and stabbed, to prevent him from entering the castle. Thus when Hans-My-Hedgehog rode up, they attackedactive, male, neutral him with bayonets, but he spurred his roosteractive, male, neutral on, flew over the gate and up to the king's window. Landing there, he shoutedactive, male, neutral to him, to give him what he had promised, or it would cost him and his daughter their lives.

Then the king told the princesspassive, male, hesitant to go out to him, in order to save his life and her own as well. She put on a white dressactive, female, hesitant, and her father gave her a carriage with six horses, magnificent servants, money, and property. She climbedactive, female, hesitant aboard and Hans-My-Hedgehog took his place beside herpassive, male, eager with his rooster and bagpipes. They said farewell and drove off.

The king thought that he would never see them again. However, it did not go as he thought it would, for when they had traveled a short distance from the city, Hans-My-Hedgehog pulled off her beautiful clothesactive, male, neutral and stuck heractive, male, neutral with his quills until she was bloody all over. "This is the reward for your deceit. Go away. I do not want you." With that he sent her back home, and she was cursednegative, female as long as she lived.

Hans-My-Hedgehog, astride his cock-rooster and carrying his bagpipes, rode onactive, male, neutral to the second kingdom where he had also helped the king find his way. This one, in contrast, had ordered that if anyone looking like Hans-My-Hedgehog should arrive, he should be saluted and brought to the royal castle with honors and with a military escort.

When the princess saw him she was horrifiednegative, female, because he looked so strangenegative, male, but she thought that nothing could be done about it, because she had promisedpassive, female, neutral her father to go with him. She welcomedactive, female, neutral Hans-My-Hedgehog, and they were married. Then he was taken to the royal table, and she sat next to himpassive, female, neutral while they ate and drank, and they were married.

That evening when it was time to go to bed, she was afraidnegative, female of his quills, but he told her to have no fear, for he would not hurt her. He told the old kingpassive, male, neutral to have four men keep watch by their bedroom door. They should make a large fire. He said that he would take off his hedgehog skin after going into the bedroom, and before getting into bed. The men should immediately pick it up and throw itactive, male, neutral into the fire, and then stay there until it was completely consumed by the fire.

When the clock struck eleven, he went into the bedroom, took off the hedgehog skin, and laidactive, male, neutral it down by the bed. The men rushed inactive, male, neutral, grabbed itactive, male, neutral, and threw itactive, male, neutral into the fire, and as soon as the fire consumed it, he was redeemed, and he lay there in bed entirely in the shape of a human. But he was as black as coal, as though he had been charred. The king sent for his physician, who washed him with good salves and balms. Then he became white and was a handsomepositive, male youngpositive, male gentlemanpositive, male.

When the princess saw what had happened, she was overjoyedpositive, female, and they got up and ate and drank. Now their wedding was celebrated for real, and Hans-My-Hedgehog inheritedpassive, male, neutral the old king's kingdom.

Some years later he traveled with his wifeactive, male, neutral to his father, and said that he was his son. But the father said that he did not have a son. He had had one, but he had been born with quills like a hedgehog and had gone off into the world. Then he said that he was the one, and the old father rejoicedactive, male, eager and returned with him to his kingdom.

My tale is done, And has gone To Gustchen's home.

Hansel and Gretel

Next to a great forest there lived a poor woodcutternegative, male who had come upon such hard times that he could scarcely provide daily bread for his wife and his two children, Hansel and Gretel. Finally he could no longer even manage this,passive, male, eager and he did not know where to turn for help.

One evening as he was lying in bed worrying about his problems,passive, male, eager his wife said to him, "Listen, man, early tomorrow take the two children, give each of them a little piece of bread, then lead them into the middle of thickest part of the woods, make a fire for them, and leave them there, for we can no longer feed them."

"No, woman," said the man, I cannot bring myself to abandon my own children to wild animals that would quickly tear them to pieces."active, male, hesitant

"If you don't do it," said the woman, "all of us will starve together," and she gave him no peace until he said yes.active, female, eager

The two children were still awake from hunger and heard everything that the mother had said to the father.passive, mixed, neutral

Gretel thought that she was doomed and began to cry pitifully,passive, female, neutral but Hansel said, "Be quiet, Gretel, and don't worry. I know what to do."active, male, eager

With that he got up, pulled on his jacket, opened the lower door, and crept outside.active, male, eager

The moon was shining brightly, and the white pebbles were glistening like silver coins. Hansel bent over and filled his jacket pockets with them, as many as would fit.active, male, eager

Then he went back into the house and said, "Don't worry, Gretel. Sleep well." Then he went back to bed, and fell asleep.

The next morning the mother came and woke them bothactive, female, eager before sunrise, "Get up, you children. We are going into the woods. Here is a little piece of bread. Take care and save it until midday."

Gretel put the bread under her apron, because Hansel's pockets were full of stones,passive, female, eager and they set forth into the woods.active, mixed, eager

After they had walked a little way,active, mixed, eager Hansel began stopping again and again and looking back toward the house.active, male, hesitant

The father said, "Hansel, why are you stopping and looking back? Pay attention now, and keep up with us."

"Oh, father, I am looking at my white cat that is sitting on the roof and wants to say good-bye to me."

The mother said, "You fool,negative, male that isn't your cat. That's the morning sun shining on the chimney."

However, Hansel had not been looking at his cat but instead had been dropping the shiny pebbles from his pocket onto the path.active, male, eager

When they arrived in the middle of the woods, the father said, "You children gather some wood, and I will make a fire so we won't freeze."

Hansel and Gretel gathered together some twigs,active, mixed, eager a pile as high as a small mountain

They set it afire, and when the flames were burning well, the mother said, "Lie down by the fire and sleep. We will go into the woods to cut down trees. Wait until we come back and get you."

Hansel and Gretel sat by the fire until midday, and then ate their bread.passive, mixed, neutral

They sat on until eveningpassive, mixed, hesitant, but the mother and father did not returnactive, mixed, eager, and no one came to get them.

When it became dark, Gretel began to cry,passive, female, neutral but Hansel said, "Wait a little until the moon comes up."

After the moon had come up, he took Gretel by the hand.active, male, eager

The pebbles were lying there like newly minted coins. Glistening, they showed them the way.

They walked throughout the entire night, and as morning was breaking, they arrived at the father's house.active, mixed, eager

The father was overjoyedpositive, male when he saw his children once more, for he had not wanted to leave them alone. The mother pretended that she too was happy, but secretly she was angry.negative, female

Not long afterward there was once again no bread in the house, and one evening Hansel and Gretel heard the mother say to the father, "The children found their way back once, and I let it be, but again we have only a half loaf of bread in the house. Tomorrow you must take them deeper into the woods, so they cannot find their way home. Otherwise there will be no help for us."

The man was very disheartened, and he thought it would be better to share the last bit with the children, but because he had done it once, he could not say no.passive, male, hesitant

Hansel and Gretel heard the parents' conversation.passive, mixed, neutral

Hansel got up and wanted to gather pebbles once again,active, male, eager but when he came to the door, he found that the mother had locked it.passive, female, neutral

Still, he comforted Gretel and said, "Just go to sleep, Gretel dear. God will help us."active, male, eager

Early the next morning they received their little pieces of breadpassive, mixed, neutral, even less than the last time.

On the way, Hansel crumbled his piece in his pocket, then often stood still, and threw crumbs onto the ground.active, male, eager

"Why are you always stopping and looking around?" said his father. "Keep walking straight ahead."

"Oh!, I can see my pigeon sitting on the roof. It wants to say good-bye to me."

"You fool,"negative, male said his mother, "that isn't your pigeon. That's the morning sun shining on the chimney."

But Hansel crumbled all of his bread and dropped the crumbs onto the path.active, male, eager

The mother took them deeper into the woods than they had ever been in their whole lifetime.active, female, eager

There they were told to sleep by a large fire, and that the parents would come and get them in the evening.

At midday Gretel shared her bread with Hansel, because he had scattered all of his along the path.active, female, eager

Midday passed, and evening passed, but no one came to get the poornegative, mixed children.

Hansel comforted Gretel and said, "Wait, when the moon comes up I will be able to see the crumbs of bread that I scattered, and they will show us the way back home."

The moon came up, but when Hansel looked for the crumbs, they were gone.active, male, eager The many thousands of birds in the woods had found them and pecked them up.

Hansel thought that he would still be able to find the way home,active, male, eager and he and Gretel set forth, but they soon became totally lost in the great wilderness.active, mixed, eager

They walked through the night and the entire next day, and then, exhaustednegative, mixed, they fell asleep. They walked another day, but they could not find their way out of the woods.active, mixed, eager

They were terribly hungry, for they had eaten only a few small berries that were growing on the ground.passive, mixed, hesitant

On the third day they walked until midday when they came to a little houseactive, mixed, eager built entirely from bread with a roof made of cake, and the windows were made of clear sugar.

"Let's sit down and eat our fill," said Hansel. "I'll eat from the roof, and Gretel, you eat from the window. That will be nice and sweet for you."

Hansel had already eaten a piece from the roof and Gretel had eaten a few round windowpanes, and she had just broken out another one when she heard a gentle voice calling out from inside:passive, mixed, neutral

Nibble, nibble, little mouse, Who is nibbling at my house?

Hansel and Gretel were so frightened that they dropped what they were holding in their hands, and immediately they saw a little woman, as old as the hills,negative, female creeping out the door.

She shook her head and said, "Oh, you dear children, where did you come from? Come inside with me, and you will be just fine."

She took them by the hand and led them into her house.active, female, eager

Then she served them a good meal:active, female, eager pancakes with sugar, apples, and nuts; and made two nice beds for them.

Hansel and Gretel went to bed, thinking it was though they were in heaven.passive, mixed, neutral

But the oldneutral, female woman was a wicked witchnegative, female who was lying in wait there for children.

She had built her house of bread in order to lure them to her, and if she captured one, she would kill him, cook him, and eat him; and for her that was a day to celebrate.active, female, eager

So she was overjoyedpositive, female that Hansel and Gretel had found their way to her.

Early the next morning, before they awoke, she got up, went to their beds, and looked at the two of them lying thereactive, female, eager so peacefully.

"They will be a good mouthful," she thought.

She grabbed Hansel and put him in a little stall,active, female, eager and when he awoke, he found himself in a cage, locked up like a young dognegative, male, and he could walk only a few steps.

Then she shook Gretel and cried,active, female, eager "Get up, lazybones!negative, female Fetch water. Go into the kitchen and cook something to eat. Your brother is locked in that stall there. I want to fatten him up, and when he is fat I am going to eat him.active, female, eager For now, you have to feed him."

Gretel was frightenednegative, female and cried, but she had to do what the witch demanded.passive, female, hesitant

Now Hansel was given the best things to eat every day, so he would get fat, but Gretel received nothing but crayfish shells.

Every day the oldneutral, female woman came and said, "Hansel, stick out your finger, so I can feel if you are fat enough yet."

But Hansel always stuck out a little bone,active, male, eager and she wondered why he didn't get any fatter.

After four weeks, one evening she said to Gretel, "Hurry up and fetch some water. Whether your brother is fat enough now or not, tomorrow I am going to slaughter him and boil him.active, female, eager In the meantime I want to start the dough that we will bake to go with him."

With a sad heart Gretel fetched the water in which Hansel was to be boiled.passive, female, hesitant

The next morning Gretel had to get up early, make a fire, and hang up the kettle with water.

"Watch it until it boils," said the witch. "I am going to make a fire in the oven and put the bread into it."

Gretel stood in the kitchen and cried tears of blood and thought that it would have been better if wild animals had devoured them in the woods,passive, female, neutral for then they would at least have died together and would not now be suffering so, and she herself would not have to be boiling the water that would kill her dear brother; and she prayed, "Dear God, save us poor children."

Then the oldneutral, female woman called, "Gretel, come here right now to the oven."

And when Gretel came, she said, "Look inside and see if the bread is nicely brown and done, for my eyes are weak, and I can't see that far. If you can't see that far either, then sit on the board, and I'll push you inside, then you can walk around inside and take a look."

But once Gretel was inside, the witchnegative, female intended to close the door, and bake her in the hot oven, and eat her as well. That is what the wicked witchnegative, male was thinking, and that is why she called Gretel.

However, God let Gretel know this, so she said, "I don't know how to do that. First show me. You sit on the board, and I will push you inside."active, female, eager

So the oldneutral, female woman sat on the board, and since she was light, Gretel pushed her all the way inside, then quickly closed the door and secured it with an iron bar.active, female, eager

The oldneutral, female woman in the hot oven began to cry and to wail, but Gretel ran away, and the oldneutral, female woman burned up miserably.

Gretel ran to Hansel and unlocked his door.active, female, eager

He jumped out,active, male, eager and they kissed each other and were overjoyed.

The whole house was filled with precious stones and pearls.

They filled their pockets, then ran away and found their way back home.active, mixed, eager

The father rejoiced when he saw them once more, for he had not had a happy day since they had been gone,positive, male and now he was a rich man.positive, male However, the mother had died.

Hansel and Gretel

Next to a great forest there lived a poor woodcutternegative, male with his wife and his two children. The boy's name was Hansel and the girl's name was Gretel. He had but little to eat, and once, when a great famine came to the land, he could no longer provide even their daily bread.passive, male, eager

One evening as he was lying in bed worrying about his problems,passive, male, eager he sighed and said to his wife, "What is to become of us? How can we feed our children when we have nothing for ourselves?"

"Man, do you know what?" answered the woman."Early tomorrow morning we will take the two children out into the thickest part of the woods, make a fire for them, and give each of them a little piece of bread, then leave them by themselves and go off to our work. They will not find their way back home, and we will be rid of them."

"No, woman," said the man. "I will not do that. How could I bring myself to abandon my own children alone in the woods? Wild animals would soon come and tear them to pieces."passive, male, eager

"Oh, you fool,"negative, female she said, "then all four of us will starve. All you can do is to plane the boards for our coffins." And she gave him no peace until he agreed.passive, female, eager

"But I do feel sorry for the poor children," said the man.

The two children had not been able to fall asleep because of their hunger, and they heard what the stepmother had said to the father.passive, mixed, neutral

Gretel cried bitter tearspassive, female, neutral and said to Hansel, "It is over with us!"

"Be quiet, Gretel," said Hansel, "and don't worry. I know what to do."

And as soon as the adults had fallen asleep, he got up, pulled on his jacket, opened the lower door, and crept outside.active, male, eager The moon was shining brightly, and the white pebbles in front of the house were glistening like silver coins. Hansel bent over and filled his jacket pockets with them, as many as would fit.

Then he went back into the house and said, "Don't worry, Gretel. Sleep well. God will not forsake us." Then he went back to bed.

At daybreak, even before sunrise, the woman came and woke the two children. Get up, you lazybones.negative, mixed We are going into the woods to fetch wood." Then she gave each one a little piece of bread, saying, "Here is something for midday. Don't eat it any sooner, for you'll not get any more."active, female, eager

Gretel put the bread under her apron, because Hansel's pockets were full of stones. Then all together they set forth into the woods. After they had walked a little way, Hansel began stopping again and again and looking back toward the house.active, male, eager

The father said, "Hansel, why are you stopping and looking back? Pay attention now, and don't forget your legs."

"Oh, father," said Hansel, "I am looking at my white cat that is sitting on the roof and wants to say good-bye to me."

The woman said, You fool,negative, male that isn't your cat. That's the morning sun shining on the chimney."

However, Hansel had not been looking at his cat but instead had been dropping the shiny pebbles from his pocket onto the path.active, male, eager

When they arrived in the middle of the woods, the father said, "You children gather some wood, and I will make a fire so you won't freeze."

Hansel and Gretel gathered together some twigs,active, mixed, eager a pile as high as a small mountain

The twigs were set afire, and when the flames were burning well, the woman said, "Lie down by the fire and rest. We will go into the woods to cut wood. When we are finished, we will come back and get you."

Hansel and Gretel sat by the fire. When midday came each one ate his little piece of bread. Because they could hear the blows of an ax, they thought that the father was nearby. However, it was not an ax. It was a branch that he had tied to a dead tree and that the wind was beating back and forth. After they had sat there a long time, their eyes grew weary and closed, and they fell sound sleep.

When they finally awoke, it was dark at night. Gretel began to cry and said, "How will we get out of woods?"

Hansel comforted her, "Wait a little until the moon comes up, and then we'll find the way."

After the full moon had come up, Hansel took his little sister by the hand.active, male, eager They followed the pebbles that glistened there like newly minted coins, showing them the way. They walked throughout the entire night, and as morning was breaking, they arrived at the father's house.active, mixed, eager

They knocked on the door, and when the woman opened it and saw that it was Hansel and Gretel, she said, You wickednegative, mixed children, why did you sleep so long in the woods? We thought that you did not want to come back."

But the father was overjoyedpositive, male when he saw his children once more, for he had not wanted to leave them alone.passive, male, eager

Not long afterward there was once again great need everywhere, and one evening the children heard the mother say to the father, "We have again eaten up everything. We have only a half loaf of bread, and then the song will be over. We must get rid of the children. We will take them deeper into the woods, so they will not find their way out. Otherwise there will be no help for us."active, female, eager

The man was very disheartened, and he thought, "It would be better to share the last bit with the children."passive, male, hesitant

But the woman would not listen to him, scolded him, and criticized him. He who says A must also say B, and because he had given in the first time, he had to do so the second time as well.

The children were still awake and had overheard the conversation. When the adults were asleep, Hansel got up again and wanted to gather pebbles as he had done before,active, male, eager but the woman had locked the door,active, female, eager and Hansel could not get out. But he comforted his little sister and said, "Don't cry, Gretel. Sleep well. God will help us."active, male, eager

Early the next morning the woman came and got the children from their beds. They received their little pieces of bread, even less than the last time.active, female, eager On the way to the woods, Hansel crumbled his piece in his pocket, then often stood still, and threw crumbs onto the ground.

"Hansel, why are you always stopping and looking around?" said his father. "Keep walking straight ahead."

"I can see my pigeon sitting on the roof. It wants to say good-bye to me."

"Fool,"negative, male said the woman, "that isn't your pigeon. That's the morning sun shining on the chimney."

But little by little Hansel dropped all the crumbs onto the path.active, male, eager The woman took them deeper into the woods than they had ever been in their whole lifetime.active, female, eager

Once again a large fire was made, and the mother said, "Sit here, children. If you get tired you can sleep a little. We are going into the woods to cut wood. We will come and get you in the evening when we are finished."

When it was midday Gretel shared her bread with Hansel, who had scattered his piece along the path.active, female, eager Then they fell asleep, and evening passed, but no one came to get the poor children.passive, mixed, eager

It was dark at night when they awoke, and Hansel comforted Gretel and said, "Wait, when the moon comes up I will be able to see the crumbs of bread that I scattered, and they will show us the way back home."active, male, eager

When the moon appeared they got up, but they could not find any crumbs,active, mixed, eager for the many thousands of birds that fly about in the woods and in the fields had pecked them up.

Hansel said to Gretel, "We will find our way," but they did not find it.

They walked through the entire night and the next day from morning until evening, but they did not find their way out of the woods.active, mixed, eager They were terribly hungry, for they had eaten only a few small berries that were growing on the ground. And because they were so tired that their legs would no longer carry them, they lay down under a tree and fell asleep.passive, mixed, eager It was already the third morning since they had left the father's house. They started walking again, but managed only to go deeper and deeper into the woods.active, mixed, eager If help did not come soon, they would perish. At midday they saw a little snow-white bird sitting on a branch. It sang so beautifully that they stopped to listen. When it was finished it stretched its wings and flew in front of them. They followed it until they came to a little house. The bird sat on the roof, and when they came closer, they saw that the little house was built entirely from bread with a roof made of cake, and the windows were made of clear sugar.

"Let's help ourselves to a good meal," said Hansel. "I'll eat a piece of the roof, and Gretel, you eat from the window. That will be sweet."

Hansel reached up and broke off a little of the roof to see how it tasted,active, male, eager while Gretel stood next to the windowpanes and was nibbling at them. Then a gentle voice called out from inside:

Nibble, nibble, little mouse, Who is nibbling at my house? The children answered: The wind, the wind, The heavenly child.

They continued to eat, without being distracted. Hansel, who very much like the taste of the roof, tore down another large piece,active, male, eager and Gretel poked out an entire round windowpane.active, female, eager Suddenly the door opened, and a woman, as old as the hills and leaning on a crutch,negative, female came creeping out. Hansel and Gretel were so frightened that they dropped what they were holding in their hands.

But the oldneutral, female woman shook her head and said, "Oh, you dear children, who brought you here? Just come in and stay with me. No harm will come to you."

She took them by the hand and led them into her house. Then she served them a good meal:active, female, eager milk and pancakes with sugar, apples, and nuts. Afterward she made two nice beds for them,active, female, eager decked in white. Hansel and Gretel went to bed, thinking they were in heaven.passive, mixed, eager But the oldneutral, female woman had only pretended to be friendly. She was a wicked witchnegative, female who was lying in wait there for children. She had built her house of bread only in order to lure them to her, and if she captured one, she would kill him, cook him, and eat him; and for her that was a day to celebrate.active, female, eager

Witches have red eyes and cannot see very far, but they have a sense of smell like animals, and know when humans are approaching.negative, female

When Hansel and Gretel came near to her, she laughed wickedlynegative, female and spoke scornfullynegative, female, "Now I have them. They will not get away from me again."active, female, eager

Early the next morning, before they awoke, she got up, went to their beds, and looked at the two of them lying there so peacefully, with their full red cheeks.positive, mixed "They will be a good mouthful," she mumbled to herself. Then she grabbed Hansel with her withered hand and carried him to a little stall, where she locked him behind a cage door.active, female, eager Cry as he might, there was no help for him.

Then she shook Gretel and cried,active, female, eager "Get up, lazybones!negative, female Fetch water and cook something good for your brother. He is locked outside in the stall and is to be fattened up. When he is fat I am going to eat him."

Gretel began to cry, but it was all for nothing. She had to do what the witch demanded.passive, female, hesitant Now Hansel was given the best things to eat every day, but Gretel received nothing but crayfish shells.

Every morning the oldneutral, female woman crept out to the stall and shouted, "Hansel, stick out your finger, so I can feel if you are fat yet."

But Hansel stuck out a little bone,active, male, eager and the oldneutral, female woman, who had bad eyes and could not see the bone, thought it was Hansel's finger, and she wondered why he didn't get fat.

When four weeks had passed and Hansel was still thin, impatience overcame her, and she would wait no longer.active, female, eager "Hey, Gretel!" she shouted to the girl, "Hurry up and fetch some water. Whether Hansel is fat or thin, tomorrow I am going to slaughter him and boil him."active, female, eager

Oh, how the poor little sister sobbed as she was forced to carry the water, and how the tears streamed down her cheeks!passive, female, hesitant "Dear God, please help us," she cried. "If only the wild animals had devoured us in the woods, then we would have died together."

"Save your slobbering," said the oldneutral, female woman. "It doesn't help you at all."

The next morning Gretel had to get up early, hang up the kettle with water, and make a fire.passive, female, hesitant

"First we are going to bake," said the oldneutral, female woman. "I have already made a fire in the oven and kneaded the dough."

She pushed poor Gretel outside to the oven,active, female, eager from which fiery flames were leaping. "Climb in," said the witch, "and see if it is hot enough to put the bread in yet." And when Gretel was inside, she intended to close the oven, and bake her, and eat her as well.

But Gretel saw what she had in mind, so she said, "I don't know how to do that. How can I get inside?"

"Stupid goose,"negative, female said the oldneutral, female woman. The opening is big enough. See, I myself could get in." And she crawled up stuck her head into the oven.

Then Gretel gave her a shove, causing her to fall in. Then she closed the iron door and secured it with a bar.active, female, eager The oldneutral, female woman began to howl frightfully. But Gretel ran away, and the godless witchnegative, female burned up miserably. Gretel ran straight to Hansel, unlocked his stall, and cried, "Hansel, we are saved. The old witchnegative, female is dead."active, female, eager

Then Hansel jumped out, like a bird from its cage when someone opens its door.active, male, eager How happy they were! They threw their arms around each other's necks, jumped with joy, and kissed one another. Because they now had nothing to fear, they went into the witch's house. In every corner were chests of pearls and precious stones.

"These are better than pebbles," said Hansel, filling his pockets.

Gretel said, "I will take some home with me as well," and she filled her apron full.active, female, eager

"But now we must leave," said Hansel, "and get out of these witch-woods."

After walking a few hours they arrived at a large body of water. "We cannot get across," said Hansel. "I cannot see a walkway or a bridge."

"There are no boats here," answered Gretel, "but there is a white duck swimming. If I ask it, it will help us across."

Then she called out:active, female, eager

Duckling, duckling, Here stand Gretel and Hansel. Neither a walkway nor a bridge, Take us onto your white back.

The duckling came up to them, and Hansel climbed onto it, then asked his little sisterneutral, female to sit down next to him.

"No," answered Gretel. "That would be too heavy for the duckling. It should take us across one at a time."

That is what the good animal did, and when they were safely on the other side, and had walked on a little while, the woods grew more and more familiar to them, and finally they saw the father's house in the distance. They began to run, rushed inside, and threw their arms around the father's neck.active, mixed, eager

The man had not had even one happy hour since he had left the children in the woods.positive, male However, the woman had died. Gretel shook out her apron, scattering pearls and precious stones around the room, and Hansel added to them by throwing one handful after the other from his pockets.

Now all their cares were at an end, and they lived happily together.

My tale is done, A mouse has run. And whoever catches it can make for himself from it a large, large fur cap.

Little Red Cap (1812)

Once upon a time there was a sweetpositive, female littleneutral, female girl. Everyone who saw her liked her, but most of all her grandmother, who did not know what to give the child next. Once she gave her a little cap made of red velvetactive, female, eager. Because it suited her so well, and she wanted to wear it all the time, she came to be known as Little Red Cappassive, female, neutral.

One day her mother said to her, "Come Little Red Cap. Here is a piece of cake and a bottle of wine. Take them to your grandmother. She is sicknegative, female and weaknegative, female, and they will do her well. Mind your manners and give her my greetings. Behave yourself on the way, and do not leave the path, or you might fall down and break the glass, and then there will be nothing for your sicknegative, female grandmother."

Little Red Cap promised to obey her motheractive, female, eager. The grandmother lived out in the woods, a half hour from the village. When Little Red Cap entered the woods a wolf came up to her. She did not know what a wickednegative, male animal he was, and was not afraid of himpassive, female, neutral.

"Good day to you, Little Red Cap."

"Thank you, wolf."

"Where are you going so early, Little Red Cap?"

"To grandmother's."

"And what are you carrying under your apron?"

"Grandmother is sicknegative, female and weaknegative, female, and I am taking her some cake and wineactive, female, eager. We baked yesterday, and they should give her strength."

"Little Red Cap, just where does your grandmother live?"

"Her house is a good quarter hour from here in the woods, under the three large oak trees. There's a hedge of hazel bushes there. You must know the place," said Little Red Cap.

The wolf thought to himself, "Now there is a tasty bite for me. Just how are you going to catch her?" Then he said, "Listen, Little Red Cap, haven't you seen the beautiful flowers that are blossoming in the woods? Why don't you go and take a look? And I don't believe you can hear how beautifully the birds are singing. You are walking along as though you were on your way to school in the village. It is very beautiful in the woods."

Little Red Cap opened her eyes and saw the sunlight breaking through the trees and how the ground was covered with beautiful flowers. She thought, "If a take a bouquet to grandmother, she will be very pleased. Anyway, it is still early, and I'll be home on time." And she ran off into the woods looking for flowers. Each time she picked one she thought that she could see an even more beautiful one a little way off, and she ran after it, going further and further into the woodsactive, female, eager. But the wolf ran straight to the grandmother's house and knocked on the dooractive, male, eager.

"Who's there?"

"Little Red Cap. I'm bringing you some cake and wineactive, male, eager. Open the door for me."

"Just press the latch," called out the grandmother. "I'm too weaknegative, female to get up."

The wolf pressed the latch, and the door opened. He stepped inside, went straight to the grandmother's bed, and ate her up. Then he took her clothes, put them on, and put her cap on his head. He got into her bed and pulled the curtains shutactive, male, eager.

Little Red Cap had run after flowers, and did not continue on her way to grandmother's until she had gathered all that she could carry. When she arrived, she found, to her surprise, that the door was openactive, female, eager. She walked into the parlor, and everything looked so strange that she thought, "Oh, my God, why am I so afraid? I usually like it at grandmother's."active, female, hesitant Then she went to the bed and pulled back the curtainsactive, female, hesitant. Grandmother was lying there with her cap pulled down over her face and looking very strangenegative, femalepassive, female, neutral.

"Oh, grandmother, what big ears you haveneutral, male!"

"All the better to hear you with."

"Oh, grandmother, what big eyes you haveneutral, male!"

"All the better to see you with."

"Oh, grandmother, what big hands you haveneutral, male!"

"All the better to grab you with!"

"Oh, grandmother, what a horribly big mouth you havenegative, male!"

"All the better to eat you with!" And with that he jumped out of bed, jumped on top of poornegative, female Little Red Cap, and ate her up. As soon as the wolf had finished this tasty bite, he climbed back into bed, fell asleep, and began to snore very loudlyactive, male, eager.

A huntsman was just passing by. He thought it strange that the oldneutral, female woman was snoring so loudlypassive, female, neutral, so he decided to take a look. He stepped inside, and in the bed there lay the wolf that he had been hunting for such a long timeactive, male, eager. "He has eaten the grandmother, but perhaps she still can be saved. I won't shoot him," thought the huntsman. So he took a pair of scissors and cut open his bellyactive, male, eager.

He had cut only a few strokes when he saw the red cap shining through. He cut a little more, and the girl jumped out and cried, "Oh, I was so frightened! It was so dark inside the wolf's body!"passive, female, eager

And then the grandmother came out alive as wellpassive, female, neutral. Then Little Red Cap fetched some large heavy stonesactive, female, eager. They filled the wolf's body with them, and when he woke up and tried to run away, the stones were so heavy that he fell down deadpassive, male, neutral.

The three of them were happy. The huntsman took the wolf's peltactive, male, eager. The grandmother ate the cake and drank the wine that Little Red Cap had broughtactive, female, eager. And Little Red Cap thought to herself, "As long as I live, I will never leave the path and run off into the woods by myself if mother tells me not toactive, female, eager."

They also tell how Little Red Cap was taking some baked things to her grandmother another time, when another wolf spoke to her and wanted her to leave the pathpassive, male, eagerpassive, female, eager. But Little Red Cap took care and went straight to grandmother'sactive, female, eager. She told her that she had seen the wolf, and that he had wished her a good day, but had stared at her in a wickednegative, male manner. "If we hadn't been on a public road, he would have eaten me uppassive, female, neutral," she said.

"Come," said the grandmother. "Let's lock the door, so he can't get inactive, female, eager."

Soon afterward the wolf knocked on the door and called out, "Open up, grandmother. It's Little Red Cap, and I'm bringing you some baked things."active, male, eager

They remained silent, and did not open the door. The wickednegative, male one walked around the house several times, and finally jumped onto the roof. He wanted to wait until Little Red Cap went home that evening, then follow her and eat her up in the darknessactive, male, eager. But the grandmother saw what he was up to. There was a large stone trough in front of the house.

"Fetch a bucket, Little Red Cap," she said. "Yesterday I cooked some sausage. Carry the water that I boiled them with to the trough." Little Red Cap carried water until the large, large trough was clear fullactive, female, eager. The smell of sausage arose into the wolf's nose. He sniffed and looked down, stretching his neck so long that he could no longer hold himself, and he began to slide. He slid off the roof, fell into the trough, and drownedpassive, male, eager. And Little Red Cap returned home happily and safelyactive, female, eager.

Little Snow-White (1812)

Once upon a time in midwinter, when the snowflakes were falling like feathers from heaven, a queen sat sewing at her window, which had a frame of black ebony wood. As she sewed she looked up at the snow and pricked her fingerpassive, female, neutral with her needle. Three drops of blood fell into the snow. The red on the white looked so beautiful that she thought to herself, "If only I had a child as white as snow, as red as blood, and as black as the wood in this frame."

Soon afterward she had a little daughter who was as white as snowneutral, female, as red as bloodneutral, female, and as black as ebony woodneutral, female, and therefore they called her Little Snow-White. And as soon as the child was born, the queen diedpassive, female, neutral.

A year later the king took himself another wife. She was a beautifulpositive, female woman, but she was proudnegative, female and arrogantnegative, female, and she could not stand it if anyone might surpass her in beauty. She had a magic mirror. Every morning she stood before it, looked at herself, and saidactive, female, eager:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? To this the mirror answered: You, my queen, are fairest of all.

Then she was satisfied, for she knew that the mirror spoke the truth.

Snow-White grew up and became ever more beautifulpositive, female. When she was seven years old she was as beautiful as the light of daypositive, female, even more beautiful than the queen herself.

One day when the queen asked her mirror:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? It answered: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White is a thousand times fairer than you.

The queen took fright and turned yellow and green with envynegative, female. From that hour on whenever she looked at Snow-White her heart turned over inside her body, so great was her hatred for the girl. The envy and pride grew ever greater, like a weed in her heart, until she had no peace day and night.

Then she summonedactive, female, eager a huntsman and said to him, "Take Snow-White out into the woods. I never want to see her again. Kill her, and as proof that she is dead bring her lungs and her liver back to me."

The huntsman obeyedpassive, male, neutral and took Snow-White into the woods. He took out his hunting knife and was about to stab it into her innocentpositive, female heart when she began to crypassive, female, neutral, saying, "Oh, dear huntsman, let me live. I will run into the wild woods and never come back."

Because she was so beautifulpositive, male the huntsman took pityactive, male, neutral on her, and he said, "Run away, you poor child."

He thought, "The wild animals will soon devour you anyway," but still it was as if a stone had fallen from his heart, for he would not have to kill her.

Just then a young boar came running by. He killed it, cut out its lungs and liver, and took them back to the queen as proof of Snow-White's death. The cook had to boil them with salt, and the wickednegative, female woman ateactive, female, eager them, supposing that she had eaten Snow-White's lungs and liver.

The poorneutral, female child was now all alone in the great forest, and she was so afraid that she just looked at all the leaves on the trees and did not know what to do. Then she began torunpassive, female, neutral. She ran over sharp stones and through thorns, and wild animals jumped at her, but they did her no harm. She ran as far as her feet could carry her, and just as evening was about to fall she saw a little house and went insidepassive, female, neutral in order to rest.

Inside the house everything was small, but so neat and clean that no one could say otherwise. There was a little table with a white tablecloth and seven little plates, and each plate had a spoon, and there were seven knives and forks and seven mugs as well. Against the wall there were seven little beds, all standing in a row and covered with snow-white sheets.

Because she was so hungry and thirsty Snow-White ate a few vegetables and a little bread from each little plate, and from each mug she drank a drop of wine. Afterward, because she was so tired, she lay down on a bed, but none of them felt right -- one was too long, the other too short -- until finally the seventh one was just right. She remained lying in it, entrusted herself to God, and fell asleep.

After dark the masters of the house returned home. They were the seven dwarfs who picked and dug for ore in the mountains. They lit their seven candles, and as soon as it was light in their house they saw that someone had been there, for not everything was in the same order as they had left it.

The first one said, "Who has been sitting in my chair?"

The second one, "Who has been eating from my plate?"

The third one, "Who has been eating my bread?"

The fourth one, "Who has been eating my vegetables?"

The fifth one, "Who has been sticking with my fork?"

The sixth one, "Who has been cutting with my knife?"

The seventh one, "Who has been drinking from my mug?"

Then the first one saw a that there was a little imprint in his bed, and said, "Who stepped on my bed?"

The others came running up and shouted, "Someone has been lying in mine as well."

But the seventh one, looking at his bed, found Snow-White lying there asleep. The seven dwarfs all came running up, and they cried out with amazement. They fetched their seven candles and shone the light on Snow-White. "Oh good heaven! Oh good heaven!" they cried. "This child is so beautifulpositive, female!"

They were so happy, that they did not wake her up, but let her continue to sleep there in the bed. The seventh dwarf had to sleep with his companions, one hour with each one, and then the night was done.

The next morning Snow-White woke up, and when she saw the seven dwarfs she was frightenednegative, female. But they were friendly and asked, "What is your name?"

"My name is Snow-White," she answered.

"How did you find your way to our house?" the dwarfs asked further.

Then she told them that her stepmother had tried to kill her, that the huntsman had spared her life, and that she had run the entire day, finally coming to their house.

The dwarfs said, "If you will keep house for us, and cook, make beds, wash, sew, and knit, and keep everything clean and orderly, then you can stay with us, and you shall have everything that you want."

"Yes," said Snow-White, "with all my heart."

So she kept house for them. Every morning they went into the mountains looking for ore and gold, and in the evening when they came back home their meal had to be ready. During the day the girl was alone.

The good dwarfs warned her, saying, "Be careful about your stepmother. She will soon know that you are here. Do not let anyone in."

Now the queen, believing that she had eaten Snow-White's lungs and liver, could only think that she was again the first and the most beautiful woman of all. She stepped before her mirror and said:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? It answered: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White, beyond the mountains With the seven dwarfs, Is still a thousand times fairer than you.

This startled the queen, for she knew that the mirror did not lie, and she realized that the huntsman had deceived her, and that Snow-White was still alive. Then she thought, and thought again, how she could kill Snow-White, for as long as long as she was not the most beautiful woman in the entire land her envynegative, female would give her no rest.

At last she thought of something. Coloring her face, she disguised herself as an old peddler womanactive, female, eager, so that no one would recognize her. In this disguise she went to the house of the seven dwarfsactive, female, eager. Knocking on the door she called out, "Beautiful wares for sale, for sale!"

Snow-White peered out the window and said, "Good day, dear woman, what do you have for sale?"

"Good wares, beautiful wares," she answered. "Bodice laces in all colors." And she took out one that was braided from colorful silk. "Would you like this one?"

"I can let that honest woman in," thought Snow-White, then unbolted the door and bought the pretty bodice lace.

"Child," said the old woman, "how you look! Come, let me lace you up properly."

The unsuspecting Snow-White stood before her and let her do up the new lacepassive, female, neutral, but the old woman pulled so quickly and so hardactive, female, eager that Snow-White could not breathe.

"You used to be the most beautiful one," said the old woman, and hurried away.

Not long afterward, in the evening time, the seven dwarfs came home. How terrified they were when they saw their dear Snow-White lying on the ground, not moving at all, as though she were dead. They lifted her up, and, seeing that she was too tightly laced, they cut the lace in two. Then she began to breathe a little, and little by little she came back to life.

When the dwarfs heard what had happened they said, "The old peddler woman was no one else but the godlessnegative, female queen. Take care and let no one in when we are not with you."

When the wickednegative, female woman returned home she went to her mirror and asked:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? The mirror answered once again: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White, beyond the mountains With the seven dwarfs, Is still a thousand times fairer than you.

When she heard that, all her blood ran to her heart because she knew that Snow-White had come back to life.

"This time," she said, "I shall think of something that will destroy you."

Then with the art of witchcraft, which she understood, she made a poisoned comb. Then she disguised herself, taking the form of a different old woman. Thus she went across the seven mountains to the seven dwarfs, knocked on the door, and called out, "Good wares for sale, for sale!"

Snow-White looked out and said, "Go on your way. I am not allowed to let anyone in."

"You surely may take a look," said the old woman, pulling out the poisoned comb and holding it up. The child liked it so much that she let herself be deceived, and she opened the door.active, female, hesitant

After they had agreed on the purchase, the old woman said, "Now let me comb your hair properly."

She had barely stuck the comb into Snow-White's hair when the poison took effect, and the girl fell down unconsciouspassive, female, neutral.

"You specimen of beauty," said the wickednegative, female woman, "now you are finished." And she walked away.

Fortunately it was almost evening, and the seven dwarfs came home. When they saw Snow-White lying on the ground as if she were dead, they immediately suspected her stepmother. They examined her and found the poisoned comb. They had scarcely pulled it out when Snow-White came to herself again and told them what had happened. Once again they warned her to be on guard and not to open the door for anyone.

Back at home the queen stepped before her mirror and said:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? The mirror answered: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But Snow-White, beyond the mountains With the seven dwarfs, Is still a thousand times fairer than you.

When the queen heard the mirror saying this, she shook and trembled with anger, "Snow-White shall die," she shouted, "if it costs me my life!"

Then she went into her most secret room -- no one else was allowed inside -- and she made a poisonedactive, female, eager, poisoned apple. From the outside it was beautiful, white with red cheeks, and anyone who saw it would want it. But anyone who might eat a little piece of it would died. Then, coloring her face, she disguised herself as a peasant woman, and thus went across the seven mountains to the seven dwarfs. She knocked on the door.

Snow-White stuck her head out the window and said, "I am not allowed to let anyone in. The dwarfs have forbidden me to do so."

"That is all right with me," answered the peasant woman. "I'll easily get rid of my apples. Here, I'll give you one of them."

"No," said Snow-White, "I cannot accept anything."

"Are you afraid of poison?" asked the old woman. "Look, I'll cut the apple in two. You eat the red half, and I shall eat the white half."

Now the apple had been so artfully made that only the red half was poisoned. Snow-White longed for the beautiful apple, and when she saw that the peasant woman was eating part of it she could no longer resist, and she stuck her hand out and took the poisoned half. She barely had a bite in her mouth when she fell to the ground dead.

The queen looked at her with a gruesomenegative, female stare, laughed loudly, and said, "White as snow, red as blood, black as ebony wood! This time the dwarfs cannot awaken you."

Back at home she asked her mirror:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? It finally answered: You, my queen, are fairest of all.

Then her enviousnegative, female heart was at rest, as well as an envious heart can be at rest.

When the dwarfs came home that evening they found Snow-White lying on the ground. She was not breathing at all. She was dead. They lifted her up and looked for something poisonous. They undid her laces. They combed her hair. They washed her with water and wine. But nothing helped. The dear child was dead, and she remained dead. They laid her on a bier, and all seven sat next to her and mourned for her and cried for three days. They were going to bury her, but she still looked as fresh as a living person, and still had her beautiful red cheeks.

They said, "We cannot bury her in the black earth," and they had a transparent glass coffin made, so she could be seen from all sides. They laid her inside, and with golden letters wrote on it her name, and that she was a princess. Then they put the coffin outside on a mountain, and one of them always stayed with it and watched over her. The animals too came and mourned for Snow-white, first an owl, then a raven, and finally a dove.

Snow-White lay there in the coffin a long, long time, and she did not decay, but looked like she was asleep, for she was still as white as snow and as red as blood, and as black-haired as ebony wood.

Now it came to pass that a prince entered these woods and happened onto the dwarfs' house, where he sought shelter for the night. He saw the coffin on the mountain with beautiful Snow-White in it, and he read what was written on it with golden letters.

Then he said to the dwarfs, "Let me have the coffin. I will give you anything you want for it."

But the dwarfs answered, "We will not sell it for all the gold in the world."

Then he said, "Then give it to me, for I cannot live without being able to see Snow-White. I will honor her and respect her as my most cherished one."

As he thus spoke, the good dwarfs felt pity for him and gave him the coffin. The prince had his servants carry it away on their shoulders. But then it happened that one of them stumbled on some brush, and this dislodged from Snow-White's throat the piece of poisoned apple that she had bitten off. Not long afterward she opened her eyes, lifted the lid from her coffin, sat up, and was alive again.

"Good heavens, where am I?" she cried out.

The prince said joyfully, "You are with me." He told her what had happened, and then said, "I love you more than anything else in the world. Come with me to my father's castle. You shall become my wife." Snow-White loved him, and she went with him. Their wedding was planned with great splendor and majesty.

Snow-White's godlessnegative, female stepmother was also invited to the feast. After putting on her beautiful clothes she stepped before her mirror and said:

Mirror, mirror, on the wall, Who in this land is fairest of all? The mirror answered: You, my queen, are fair; it is true. But the young queen is a thousand times fairer than you.

The wickednegative, female woman uttered a curse, and she became so frightened, so frightened, that she did not know what to do. At first she did not want to go to the wedding, but she found no peace. She had to go and see the young queen. When she arrived she recognized Snow-White, and terrorized, she could only stand there without moving.

Then they put a pair of iron shoes into burning coals. They were brought forth with tongs and placed before her. She was forced to step into the red-hot shoes and dance until she fell down deadpassive, female, hesitant.

Rumpelstiltskin (1857)

Once upon a time there was a millerneutral, male who was poornegative, male, but who had a beautifulpositive, female daughter. Now it happened that he got into a conversation with the king, and to make an impression on him he said, "I have a daughter who can spin straw into gold."passive, male, eager

The king said to the miller, "That is an art that I really like. If your daughter is as skillful as you say, then bring her to my castle tomorrow, and I will put her to the testactive, male, eager."

When the girl was brought to him he led her into a room that was entirely filled with straw. Giving her a spinning wheel and a reel, he said, "Get to work now. Spin all night, and if by morning you have not spun this straw into gold, then you will have to die."passive, female, hesitant Then he himself locked the roomactive, male, eager, and she was there all alone.

The poor miller's daughter sat there, and for her life she did not know what to do. She had no idea how to spin straw into gold. She became more and more afraid, and finally began to crypassive, female, neutral.

Then suddenly the door opened. A littleneutral, male man stepped inside and said, "Good evening, Mistress Miller, why are you crying so?"

"Oh," answered the girl, "I am supposed to spin straw into gold, and I do not know how to do it."

The littleneutral, male man said, "What will you give me if I spin it for you?"

"My necklace," said the girl.

The littleneutral, male man took the necklace, sat down before the spinning wheel, and whir, whir, whir, three times pulled, and the spool was full. Then he put another one on, and whir, whir, whir, three times pulled, and the second one was full as well. So it went until morning, and then all the straw was spun, and all the spools were filled with gold.

At sunrise the king came, and when he saw the gold he was surprised and happy, but his heart became even more greedynegative, male for gold. He had the miller's daughter taken to another room filled with straw. It was even larger, and he ordered her to spin it in one nightactive, male, eager, if she valued her life.

The girl did not know what to do, and she criedpassive, female, neutral. Once again the door opened, and the little neutral, male man appeared. He said, "What will you give me if I spin the straw into gold for you?"passive, male, eager

"The ring from my finger," answered the girlactive, female, hesitant.

The littleneutral, male man took the ring, and began once again to whir with the spinning wheel. By morning he had spun all the straw into glistening goldactive, male, eager. The king was happy beyond measure when he saw it, but he still did not have his fill of gold. He had the miller's daughter taken to a still larger room filled with straw, and said, "Tonight you must spin this too. If you succeed you shall become my wife." He thought, "Even if she is only a miller's daughter, I will not find a richer wife in all the world."

When the girl was alone the littleneutral, male man returned for a third time. He said, "What will you give me if I spin the straw this time?"

"I have nothing more that I could give you," answered the girl.

"Then promise me, after you are queen, your first child."

"Who knows what will happen," thought the miller's daughter, and not knowing what else to do, she promised the little manneutral, male what he demandedactive, female, hesitant. In return the little manneutral, male once again spun the straw into gold.

When in the morning the king came and found everything just as he desired, he married her, and the beautifulpositive, female miller's daughterneutral, female became queenpassive, female, neutral.

A year later she brought a beautiful childpositive, female to the world. She thought no more about the little manneutral, male, but suddenly he appeared in her room and said, "Now give me that which you promised."

The queen took fright and offered the little man all the wealth of the kingdom if he would let her keep the child, but the little manneutral, male said, "No. Something living is dearer to me than all the treasures of the world."

Then the queen began lamenting and crying so much that the little manneutral, male took pity on her and said, "I will give you three days' time. If by then you know my name, then you shall keep your child."

The queen spent the entire night thinking of all the names she had ever heard. Then she sent a messenger into the country to inquire far and wide what other names there wereactive, female, eager. When the little manneutral, male returned the next day she began with Kaspar, Melchior, Balzer, and said in order all the names she knew. After each one the little manneutral, male said, "That is not my name."

The second day she sent inquiries into the neighborhood as to what names people hadactive, female, eager. She recited the most unusual and most curious names to the little manneutral, male: "Is your name perhaps Beastrib? Or Muttoncalf? Or Legstring?"

But he always answered, "That is not my name."

On the third day the messenger returned and said, "I have not been able to find a single new name, but when I was approaching a high mountain in the corner of the woods, there where the fox and the hare say good-night, I saw a little housepassive, male, neutral. A fire was burning in front of the house, and an altogether comicalneutral, male little manneutral, male was jumping around the fire, hopping on one leg and calling out:

Today I'll bake; tomorrow I'll brewactive, male, eager, Then I'll fetch the queen's new childactive, male, eager, It is good that no one knows, Rumpelstiltskin is my name.

You can imagine how happy the queen was when she heard that name. Soon afterward the littleneutral, male man came in and asked, "Now, Madame Queen, what is my name?"

She first asked, "Is your name Kunz?"

"No."

"Is your name Heinz?"

"No."

"Is your name perhaps Rumpelstiltskin?"

"The devil told you that! The devil told you thatpassive, female, eager!" shouted the little manneutral, male, and with anger he stomped his right foot so hard into the ground that he fell in up to his waist. Then with both hands he took hold of his left foot and ripped himself up the middle in twoactive, male, eager.

The Robber Bridegroom (1857)

Once upon a time there was a miller who had a beautifulpositive, female daughter. When she came of age he wished that she was provided for and well married. He thought, "If a respectable suitorpositive, male comes and asks for her hand in marriage, I will give her to him."passive, male, eager

Not long afterward a suitor came who appeared to be very richpositive, male, and because the miller could find no fault with him, he promised his daughter to him.passive, male, eager

The girl, however, did not like him as much as a bride should like her bridegroom. She did not trust him, and whenever she saw him or thought about him, she felt within her heart a sense of horror.negative, male

One time he said to her, "You are engaged to marry me, but you have never once paid me a visit."

The girl replied, "I don't know where your house is."

Then the bridegroom said, "My house is out in the dark woods."

Looking for an excuse, she said that she would not be able to find the way there.passive, female, hesitant

The bridegroom said, "Next Sunday you must come out to me. I have already invited guests. I will make a trail of ashes, so that you can find your way through the woods."active, male, eager

When Sunday came, and it was time for the girl to start on her way, she became frightenednegative, female, although she herself did not know exactly why. In order to mark the path, she filled both her pockets full of peas and lentils.active, female, hesitant At the entrance of the forest there was a trail of ashes, which she followed, but at every step she threw a couple of peas to the ground, to the right and to the left. She walked almost the whole day until she came to the middle of the woods, where it was the darkest, and there stood a solitary house. She did not like it, because it looked so dark and sinister. She went inside, but no one was there.active, female, hesitant It was totally quiet.

Suddenly a voice called out:

Turn back, turn back, you young bride.positive, female You are in a murderer'snegative, male house.

The girl looked up and saw that the voice came from a bird, which was hanging in a cage on the wall. It cried out again:

Turn back, turn back, you youngneutral, female bride. You are in a murderer'snegative, male house.

Then the beautifulpositive, female bride went from one room to another, walking through the whole house, but it was entirely empty, and not a human soul was to be found. Finally she came to the cellar.active, female, hesitant A very oldneutral, female woman was sitting there shaking her head.

"Could you tell me," said the girl, "if my bridegroom lives here?"

"Oh, you poor child," replied the oldneutral, female woman, "where did you come from? You are in a murderer'snegative, male den. You think you are a bride soon to be married, but it is deathnegative, male that you will be marrying. Look, they made me put a large kettle of water on the fire. When they have captured you, they will chop you to pieces without mercy, cook you, and eat you, for they are cannibalsnegative, male. If I do not show you compassion and save you, you are doomed."

With this the oldneutral, female woman led her behind a large barrel where she could not be seen.

"Be quiet as a mouse." she said. "Do not make a sound or move, or all will be over with you. Tonight when the robbers are asleep we will escape. I have long waited for an opportunity."passive, female, eager

This had scarcely happened when the godless bandnegative, male came home. They were dragging with them another maiden.active, male, eager They were drunk and paid no attention to her screams and sobs.

They gave her wine to drink,active, male, eager three glasses full, one glass of white, one glass of red, and one glass of yellow, which caused her heart to break. Then they ripped off her fine clothes, laid her on a table, chopped her beautiful body in pieces and sprinkled salt on it.active, male, eager The poornegative, female bride behind the barrel trembled and shook, for she saw well what fate the robbers had planned for her.

One of them noticed a gold ring on the murderednegative, female girl's little finger. Because it did not come off easily, he took an ax and chopped the finger off,active, male, eager but it flew into the air and over the barrel, falling right into the bride's lap. The robber took a light and looked for it, but could not find it.

Then another one said, "Did you look behind the large barrel?"

But the oldneutral, female woman cried out, "Come and eat. You can continue looking in the morning. That finger won't run away from you."active, female, eager

Then the robbers said, "The oldneutral, female woman is right." They gave up their search and sat down to eat. The oldneutral, female woman poured a sleeping-potion into their wine,active, female, eager so that they soon lay down in the cellar and fell asleep, snoring.

When the bride heard them snoring she came out from behind the barrel, and had to step over the sleepers, for they lay all in rows on the ground. She was afraid that she might awaken one of them, but God helped her, and she got through safely.active, female, eager

The oldneutral, female woman went upstairs with her, opened the door, and they hurried out of the murderer's den as fast as they could.active, female, eager

The wind had blown away the trail of ashes, but the peas and lentils had sprouted and grown up, and showed them the way in the moonlight. They walked all night, arriving at the mill the next morning. Then the girl told her father everything, just as it had happened.active, female, eager

When the wedding day came, the bridegroom appeared.active, male, eager The miller had invited all his relatives and acquaintances. As they sat at the table, each one was asked to tell something. The bride sat still and said nothing.passive, female, hesitant

Then the bridegroom said to the bride, "Come, sweetheart, don't you know anything? Tell us something, like the others have done."

She answered:

Then I will tell about a dream. I was walking alone through the woods, when finally I came to a house. Inside there was not a single human soul, but on the wall there was a bird in a cage. It cried out:

Turn back, turn back, you youngneutral, female bride.

You are in a murderer'snegative, male house.

Then it cried out the same thing again. Darling, it was only a dream. Then I went through all the rooms. They were all empty, and there was something so eerie in there. Finally I went down into the cellar, and there sat a very oldneutral, female woman, shaking her head. I asked her, "Does my bridegroom live in this house?"

She answered, "Alas poor child, you have gotten into a murderer's den. Your bridegroom does live here, but he intends to chop you to pieces and kill you, and then he intends to cook you and eat you."negative, male

Darling, it was only a dream. After that the oldneutral, female woman hid me behind a large barrel.active, female, eager I had scarcely hidden myself there when the robbers came home, dragging a girl with them. They gave her three kinds of wine to drink:active, male, eager white, red, and yellow, which caused her heart to stop beating. Darling, it was only a dream. After that they took off her fine clothes, and chopped her beautiful bodypositive, female to pieces on a table, then sprinkled salt on it.active, male, eager Darling, it was only a dream. Then one of the robbers saw that there was still a ring on her ring finger. Because it was hard to get the ring off, he took an ax and chopped off the finger.active, male, eager The finger flew through the air behind the large barrel, and fell into my lap. And here is the finger with the ring.

With these words she pulled out the finger and showed it to everyone who was there.active, female, eager

The robber, who had during this story become as white as chalk,negative, male jumped up and tried to escape,active, male, eager but the guests held him fast, and turned him over to the courts. Then he and his whole band were executed for their shameful deeds.active, female, eager

The Robber Bridegroom

A princess had been promised in marriage to a prince. He asked her a number of times to visit him in his castle, but she always declined,passive, female, hesitant because the way there led through a great forest, and she was afraid of getting lost.

If that was her only concern, said the prince, then he would help her by tying a ribbon to every tree, so that she could not lose her way.active, male, eager

For a while she attempted to further postpone her visit,passive, female, hesitant as though she were secretly afraid, but finally she ran out of excuses, and one day she had to go there. She walked through deep, deep woods from morning until evening,active, female, hesitant coming at last to a large house. Everything was quiet inside. There was only an oldneutral, female woman there, sitting just outside the door.

"Could you tell me if the prince, my bridegroom, lives here?"

"My child," answered the woman, "it is a good thing that you arrived just now when the prince is not at home. I had to fill a large kettle with water, for they intend to kill you, cook you, and then eat you."

Just then the prince and his band came home from their raid. However, because the oldneutral, female woman had sympathy with the bride's youth and beauty,positive, female she said to her, before anyone noticed her, "Quick, go down into the cellar and hide yourselfactive, female, eager behind the large barrel!"

The princess had hardly slipped behind the barrel when the band of robbers came into the cellar, bringing with them an oldneutral, female woman= whom they had captured.active, male, eager From her corner the princess could see everything that was happening without herself being noticed, and she saw that the oldneutral, female woman was her grandmother. The robbers took the oldneutral, female grandmother and murdered her.active, male, eager Then they took all the rings off her fingers,active, male, eager one after the other. However, the ring from her ring finger would not come off, so one of them picked up an ax and chopped off the finger.active, male, eager The finger flew behind the barrel and fell right into the princess's lap.

After the robbers had looked around for the finger for a long time, one of them said, "Did you look behind the large barrel?"

"It would be better to wait until it's light to continue looking," said another. "We'll look tomorrow morning, and then we'll soon find the ring."

After this the band lay down to sleep there in the same cellar.passive, male, neutral As soon as they were asleep and snoring, the bride came out from behind the barrel.active, female, eager They were all lying there in rows, and she would have to walk over all the sleeping men to reach the door. She carefully put her foot down between them, fearing always that she might awaken one of them, but fortunately that did not happen. After reaching the door she was once again in the woods, and because the moon shone brightly, she followed the ribbons until she arrived back home.active, female, eager

She told her father everything that had happened to her,active, female, eager and he immediately ordered an entire regiment to surround his castle,active, male, eager as soon as the bridegroom arrived there. That happened. The bridegroom came that very day and immediately asked why she hadn't come to visit him yesterdayactive, male, eager as she had promised.

She said, "I had a very bad dream.active, male, eager I dreamed that I went to a house. An oldneutral, female woman was sitting just outside the door, and she said to me, 'It is good that you came when no one is at home, for I have to tell you, that I had to fill a large kettle with water, and they intend to kill you, and boil you, and then eat you.' Even as she spoke, the robbers came home, and before anyone noticed me, the oldneutral, female woman said, 'Quick, go down into the cellar and hide yourself behind the large barrel.'active, female, eager I was hardly there when the robbers came down the cellar stairs. They were draggingactive, male, eager an oldneutral, female woman with them, whom they took hold of and murdered. After they had murderedactive, male, eager the oldneutral, female woman, they began to pull all the rings off her fingers,active, male, eager one after the other, but the ring on her ring finger wouldn't come off, so one of them picked up an ax and chopped away at it until itactive, male, eager flew into the air, and it came down behind the barrel right into my lap, and here I have the finger!"

With these words she suddenly pulled the finger from her pocket.active, female, eager

When the bridegroom saw and heard these things he turned as white as chalk with fear.negative, male He tried to flee by jumping out the window,active, male, eager but the sentries were standing below. They captured him and his entire band, and all of them were executed as a reward for their wickednegative, male deeds.active, male, eager

The Singing Bone (1819)

Once upon a time in a certain country there was great concern about a wild boar that was destroying the peasants' fields, killing the cattle, and ripping people apart with its tusks. The king promised a large reward to anyone who could free the land from this plagueactive, male, eager, but the beast was so large and strong that no one dared to go near the woods where it lived. Finally the king proclaimed that whoever could capture or kill the wild boar should have his only daughter in marriageactive, male, eager.

Now in this country there lived two brothers, sons of a poor mannegative, male. They declared that they dared to attempt the taskactive, male, eager. The olderneutral, male one, who was craftynegative, male and shrewdnegative, male, did so out of pride. The youngerneutral, male one, who was innocentpositive, male and simplepositive, male, did so because of his kind heartpositive, male.

The king said, "In order to be more sure of finding the beast, you should enter the woods from opposite sides."

Thus the older oneneutral, male entered the woods from the westactive, male, neutral, and the younger oneneutral, male from the east.

After the younger oneneutral, male had walked a little while, a little dwarfneutral, male stepped up to himactive, male, neutral. He held a black spear in his hand and said, "I am giving you this spear because your heart is innocentpositive, male and goodpositive, male.active, male, eager With it you can confidently attack the wild boar. It will do you no harm."

He thanked the dwarf, put the spear on his shoulder, and walked on fearlesslypositive, male.active, male, eager

Before long he saw the beast. It attacked him, but he held the spear toward it, and in its blind fury it ran into the spear with such force that its heart was slashed in twopassive, male, neutral.

Then he put the monster on his back and turned towards home, intending to take it to the kingactive, male, eager.

Emerging from the other side of the woods, he came to a house where people were making merry drinking wine and dancingactive, male, neutral. His olderneutral, male brother was there too. Thinking that the boar would not run away from him any time soon, he had decided to drink himself some real couragepassive, male, neutral. When he saw his younger brother coming out of the woods with his booty, his enviousnegative, male and evilnegative, male heart gave him no peace.

He called out to himactive, male, eager, "Come in, dear brotherpositive, male. Rest and refresh yourself with a beaker of wine."

The youngerneutral, male brother, suspecting no evil, went in and told him about the goodpositive, male dwarf who had given him the spear with which he had killed the boaractive, male, eager.

The olderneutral, male brother kept him there until eveningactive, male, eager, and then they set forth togetheractive, male, neutral. After dark they came to a bridge over a brook, and the olderneutral, male brother =let the younger oneneutral, male go firstpassive, male, eager. When the youngerneutral, male brother reached the middle above the water, the olderneutral, male one gave him such a blow from behind that he fell down deadpassive, male, neutralactive, male, eager.

He buried him beneath the bridge, took the boar, and delivered it to the king, pretending that he had killed itactive, male, eager. With this he received the king's daughter in marriagepassive, male, eager.

When his youngerneutral, male brother did not return he said, "The boar must have ripped him apart," and every one believed it.

But as nothing remains hidden from God, this black deed was also to come to light.

After many long years a shepherdneutral, male was driving his herd across the bridge and saw a little snow-white bone lying in the sand belowpassive, male, neutral. Thinking that it would make a good mouthpiece, he climbed down, picked it up, and then carved out of it a mouthpiece for his hornactive, male, eager. When he blew into it for the first time, to his great astonishment the bone began to sing by itself:

Oh, my dear shepherdpositive, male, You are blowing on my little bone. My brother killed meactive, male, eager, And buried me beneath the bridgeactive, male, eager, To get the wild boor For the daughter of the king.

"What a wonderful horn," said the shepherd. "It sings by itself. I must take it to the king."

When he brought it before the king, the horn again began to sing its little song. The king understood it well, and had the earth beneath the bridge dug upactive, male, eager. Then the whole skeleton of the murdered man came to light.

The wickednegative, male brother could not deny the deed. He was sewn into a sack and drowned alivepassive, male, hesitant. The murderedpassive, male, neutral man's bones were laid to rest in a beautiful grave in the churchyardpassive, male, neutral.